It is a destination that evokes images of idyllic
beaches with white sands and crystal-clear waters, a
tropical paradise famous not only for its stunning
natural beauty but also for its vibrant culture
and hospitality.
Here travelers from all over the world find a
perfect escape to relax and enjoy nature
at its finest, with an ideal
climate, rich marine and terrestrial biodiversity, as
well as a wide range of tourist activities.
We are talking about Punta Cana, but what is this
place, where exactly is it located and why has it
become so popular as a tourist destination
for travelers from the United States and Europe, as
well as Central and South American countries?
On September 26, 2023, a
Caribbean country reached the goal of 10
million tourists in a year, an unprecedented
milestone in the country's tourism and
the entire region.
Within this very important achievement for this
Caribbean country, there is an undisputed protagonist and it is
precisely Punta Cana.
Punta Cana is a town located in the east
of the Dominican Republic, specifically it is located
east of the La Altagracia province,
municipality of Higüey, Verón Punta Cana district.
The Punta Cana area begins to the
north with Arena Gorda beach, followed
by the famous Bávaro beach and including El Cortecito
beach, Cabeza de Toro, Juanillo beach, Macao
beach and Uvero Alto beach, among others.
The coastline of the Punta Cana area
extends for about 95 kilometers of coast,
with the Bávaro area being the most
extensive beach, considered by the government of the Dominican
Republic as a national treasure for the richness
of its flora and fauna and for the
natural beauties that can be appreciated there.
The origins of Punta Cana date back to
the year 1969 when a group of American investors
bought about 77 square kilometers of territory that
had not been developed or worked, beyond
small fishing villages on the coast.
The great jewel in the crown of the Dominican
Republic was created thanks to the initiatives of
businessman Frank Rainieri, an important Dominican businessman who
joined these American investors and convinced
them to bet on tourism in the
Punta Cana area, instead of logging
that land and exporting the wood and
soft sand to other areas like Puerto Rico.
All investors, Rainieri included, were thus aware
of the infinite potential of the beaches, the coral
reef and the multiple possibilities that existed
to exploit a virgin area and thus build
a tourist empire.
In 1970 Frank Rainieri decided to name this
previously impenetrable area Punta Cana, its name is
due to the fact that it is located at the
easternmost point of the island and the word
cana which comes from an indigenous word that
means virgin jungle.
From that moment Punta Cana grew exponentially
with large resorts of the best hotel groups,
the creation of a recreational and sports marina
and the inauguration of an international airport today
the busiest in the Dominican Republic.
In its beginnings, relevant names such as the
late designer Oscar de la Renta and the
famous Spanish singer Julio Iglesias were interested in
Punta Cana and invested in it being great
precursors of the tourist success of the area.